Based on and inspired by the teachings of Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi, this series
シュリ・マタジ・ニルマラ・デヴィの教えに基づき 着想を得たこのシリーズ
aims to explore the evolutionary relationship between two interconnected domains
2つの相互に関連した領域間の 進化的関係を探求することを目的とする
expressing human awareness at the gross and subtle levels.
雑粗なレベルと精妙なレベルで 人間の意識を解説します
It endeavors to elucidate this complex interplay between the current scientific understanding
現在の科学的理解と
of human neuroanatomy; the autonomic nervous system in particular,
人間の神経解剖学、特に自律神経系
and the so-called subtle system as described in the traditional literature on yoga.
ヨガの伝統的な文献に記載されている 精妙なシステムです
Ultimately, the series tries to bring its viewers along this exploratory journey
最終的に、このシリーズは視聴者を 探求の旅に連れて行こうとしている
to experience these relationships through meditation as taught by Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi.
シュリ・マタジ・ニルマラ・デヴィが導く 瞑想を通してこれらの関係を体験します
The human brain is a universe within us, and understanding its complex geography
人間の脳は私たちの中の宇宙です その複雑な地理を理解することは
is a grand adventure of our time, said David Van Essen.
現代の壮大な冒険と デイヴィッド・ヴァン・エッセン氏は語った
Also, the relationship between the brain and spirituality has been studied
様々な分野で脳と精神性の関係も
by several different fields,
研究されています
and we are also on this very fascinating exploration
そして私たちもこの非常に魅力的な探究に
with our esteemed guest, Dr. Ashish Pradhan,
尊敬するゲストのアシシュ・プラダン博士 と共に取り組んでいます
who is a neurologist, a meditation practitioner, and a coach.
神経科医、瞑想実践者、コーチでもあります
So without any delay, I would like to welcome Dr. Ashish on the program.
それでは、早速、アシシュ博士を この番組に迎えたいと思います
Welcome, doctor.
ようこそ、博士
How are you?
元気ですか？
I'm very well, thanks, Monika.
とても元気です ありがとう、モニカ
Glad to see you again.
また会えて嬉しいです
It's really nice always talking to you.
いつもお話できて本当に嬉しいです
You bring such wealth of information,
あなたは豊富な情報を持ってきてくれて
and I am really looking forward to talking to you
あなたとお話できることを本当に楽しみにしています
about the sixth energy center today.
今日は6番目のエネルギーセンターについて
We would like to start with that question
この質問から始めたいと思います
of the relationship between the sixth energy center and the autonomic nervous system,
第６エネルギーセンターと自律神経系の関係について
and what organs the center controls.
そしてそのセンターがどの器官を制御するか？
As we have seen in the first part of this series,
このシリーズの第1部で見てきたように
the first five energy centers,
最初の5つのエネルギーセンター
the way the energy center potentially looks after the plexuses,
神経叢をどのように管理するか
and through the plexuses
そして神経叢を通して
of the autonomic nervous system has influence over various organs
自律神経系は体内で
within the body.
様々な臓器に影響を及ぼしています
So today, we are going to talk about again,
今日はまた次のことについてお話しします
a very important, critical center.
非常に重要で、決定的なセンターです
So this is the sixth energy center, the so-called Agnya chakra.
これが6番目のエネルギーセンター いわゆるアグニャチャクラです
A lot has been written about it in multiple spiritual treatises,
多くの精神的な論文で書かれてきました
It is also referred to as the third eye in spirituality.
スピリチュアルの世界では 第三の目とも呼ばれています
The Agnya chakra, or the sixth energy center,
アグニャチャクラ または第６のエネルギーセンターは
is, as all of these energy centers go, very, very subtle.
これらすべてのエネルギー センターと同様に これは非常に精妙なものです
It is located at a midpoint, one might say,
額の中央から後頭部に線を引くと
if we draw a line from the center of the forehead to the back,
丁度中間点に位置しています
and from the top of the ears,
そして両耳間にも線を引くと交差する場所は
where it crosses, at that intersection deep within our brain.
私たちの脳の奥深くにある交差点です
The physical manifestation of this energy center,
このエネルギーセンターの物理的な現れは
not the energy center itself, but the manifestation of this,
エネルギーセンターそのものではなく
could be in the form of the optic chiasma.
視交叉の形をとる可能性があります
What is optic chiasma?
視交叉とは何ですか？
So, we have our eyes and the retina
私たちには目と網膜があります
that is at the back of the eye, that is the back end.
それは目の奥、つまり後端にあります
From the retina, you have nerves, and these nerves have their cell bodies.
網膜からは神経が伸びており 神経には細胞体があります
The axons from these bodies form the nerves,
これらの小体から伸びた軸索が神経を形成し
which together make up the optic nerve.
これらが集まって視神経を構成します
The optic nerve is a collection of these axons, or these long tails.
視神経はこれらの軸索 つまり長い尾の集合体です
And the optic nerves from each, the left and the right eye,
そして左右の目の視神経は
they go back and they cross over.
戻って来て、交差します
That's called optic chiasma.
それは視交叉と呼ばれます
And they cross over and then they go and they terminate at the back of the brain,
そしてそれらは交差し 脳の後ろで終わります
in what is called the occipital cortex.
後頭葉皮質と呼ばれる部分にあります
So the impulses from the eye, the light that goes in
目から発せられる刺激、入ってくる光は
through our pupils falls on the retina, creates a chemical reaction,
瞳孔を通して網膜に当たり、化学反応を起こし
and that impulse travels back and through the various connections that it has,
そしてその衝動は 様々なつながりを通じて過去へと伝わり
it interprets vision, or what it is that we are seeing.
それは視覚、つまり私たちが 見ているものを解釈します
So the physical manifestation is considered to be the optic chiasma,
したがって、物理的な現れは 視交叉であると考えられています
but that's not the energy center.
しかし、それはエネルギーのセンターではありません
This energy center controls our eyes,
このエネルギーセンターは 私たちの目を制御します
our vision in terms of what it sees, what it interprets.
私たちの視覚は、何を見て、何を解釈するか という点において重要です
So that's the first part.
これが最初の部分です
The second organ this energy center relates to is the master,
このエネルギーセンターが関係する 2番目の器官は指揮です
or the conductor of the orchestra.
オーケストラの指揮者を考えてみましょう
You see, like a big philharmonic orchestra,
大きなフィルハーモニーオーケストラのように
there is a conductor - and that conductor is the hypothalamus.
そこには指揮者がいます その指揮者は視床下部です
The hypothalamus is a very small organ situated in the middle of our brain.
視床下部は脳の中央に位置する 非常に小さな器官です
And we'll talk more about it also in the context of the limbic system,
大脳辺縁系の文脈でも これについてさらに話します
which is the seven so-called energy center complex.
いわゆる 7 つのエネルギー センターの 複合体です
But the hypothalamus is an organ that sits at the crossroads
しかし、視床下部は 内分泌系と神経系間の
between the endocrine system and the nervous system.
岐路に立つ器官です
So it secretes a number of hormones.
つまり、数多くのホルモンが分泌されるのです
And these hormones in turn control other endocrine organs,
そしてこれらのホルモンは
such as the pituitary, such as the adrenal cortex,
下垂体、副腎皮質
such as the male and the female reproductive endocrine systems
男性と女性の生殖内分泌系
that give rise to the ovarian cycle or the spermatogenesis in males,
卵巣周期や男性の精子形成を引き起こし
ovarian cycles in females.
女性の卵巣周期等の 内分泌器官を制御します
So the hypothalamus has four or five key functions.
つまり、視床下部には4つまたは 5つの重要な機能があるのです
And the first one is to maintain the internal homeostasis
まず第一に体内の恒常性を維持することです
by regulating the temperature and the basic biological functions
体温と基本的な生物学的機能を
through the autonomic nervous system.
自律神経を通して調節します
So that includes our blood pressure, that includes our thirst,
血圧や喉の渇きなども含まれます
our hunger or our appetite.
私たちの空腹や食欲は
It controls our urges.
私たちの衝動をコントロールします
It regulates our body temperature as well.
体温も調節します
It has endocrine functions,
内分泌機能があり
and through the hormones it secretes,
そして分泌されるホルモンを通して
it also controls the autonomic nervous system
自律神経系も制御します
via these secretions.
体内分泌物を介して行います
So say, for example, the adrenal cortex secretes cortisol,
例えば、副腎皮質がコルチゾールを分泌すると
and that is our stress hormone.
私たちのストレスホルモンです
So flight and fight reactions, for example,
例えば逃走反応や闘争反応など
which is a very well-known response within human physiology,
これは人間の生理学では非常によく知られた反応であり
you see something that is a grave danger, you run away from it.
何か重大な危険を見たら あなたはそこから逃げます
Or if it is something you want to overcome, you fight it.
あるいは、克服したいことであれば 向き合います
So all of these are controlled through this hormonal system.
これらすべてはこのホルモン系を通じて 制御されているのです
The hormonal system receives input -
ホルモン系は入力を受け取ります
the hypothalamus gets signals from multiple nervous systems.
視床下部は複数の神経系から
This enables it
信号を受け取ります
to control the functioning of the body.
これにより体の機能を制御します
And that hypothalamus is believed to be under the control of this sixth energy center.
そして視床下部はこの第6のエネルギーセンターの 制御下にあると考えられています
So you can say that the sixth energy center practically is the lord and master
つまり、第六のエネルギーセンターは 実質的に主でありマスターであると言えます
or mistress of the autonomic nervous system.
または自律神経系の女王と言えます
So as part of this series, we have now reached a point
このシリーズの一環として 私たちは今、ある段階に到達しました
where we talk about the master control of this entire orchestra,
オーケストラ全体の指揮者が
and that is the hypothalamus.
視床下部です
So that is another very important organ
さらにもう１つの非常に重要な器官があります
that this center refers to.
このセンターが言及するもの
The third organ that we would want to consider in this context
この文脈で考慮したい3番目の器官は
is the pineal gland.
松果体です
The pineal gland is a very, very small body that also sits very close to the hypothalamus.
松果体は非常に小さな器官で 視床下部に非常に近いところにあります
And this pineal body secretes a hormone you're all familiar with,
そしてこの松果体は皆さんもよくご存知の ホルモンを分泌します
it's called melatonin.
それはメラトニンと呼ばれています
And melatonin controls our sleep cycle.
そしてメラトニンは睡眠サイクルを制御します
It's extremely important.
それは非常に重要です
Anyone who's crossed time zones knows jet lag -
時差を越えた経験のある人なら 誰でも時差ボケを経験するでしょう
it's caused by the circadian rhythm,
それは概日リズムによって引き起こされます
the 24-hour sleep cycle controlled by melatonin.
メラトニンによって制御される24時間の睡眠サイクル
As the sun goes down, as the light goes down,
太陽が沈むと光が消えるにつれて
melatonin secretion starts going up.
メラトニンの分泌が増え始めます
And that is controlled by the pineal gland.
そしてそれは松果体によって制御されます
So within that framework, if we go back to the Sahaj subtle system,
その枠組みの中で、サハジャの 精妙なシステムを考慮すれば
you have the left side, which is the so-called passive side,
左側はいわゆる受動的な側面で
you have the right side, the so-called active side
右側は能動的な側面です
that we have in the subtle system within our body,
私たちの体内の精妙なシステムには
and then of course, the evolutionary side, which is the central channel.
進化の側面を持つ 中央のチャネルもあります
So you can see how there is a beautiful correlation between the function
関数と関数の間に美しい相関関係が あることがわかります
of the hypothalamus by regulating the body's requirements.
視床下部の働きにより 体の必要量を調節します
In the morning, we feel hungry, at night, not so much after we have had the day,
朝はお腹が空くが、一日の終わりの夜には それほど空腹を感じない
the whole body temperature actually starts falling down towards the evening,
夕方になると体温は下がり始めます
and it reaches its lowest temperature at night,
夜間は最低気温となり
which is why we sleep better in the cooler environments.
涼しい環境で 私たちはよりよく眠れるのです
If it's very hot, we can't sleep very well.
とても暑いと、よく眠れません
And it is also believed that when the body temperature starts going down,
そして体温が下がり始めると
it starts inducing the state that we call sleep,
睡眠と呼ばれる状態を引き起こし始めます
that we just lie down and go to sleep.
ただ横になって眠るだけです
Through this energy center, we can say that
このエネルギーセンターを通して
by monitoring our internal body through the autonomic nervous system,
自律神経系を通して 体内の状態を監視することで
by managing our sleep cycle,
睡眠サイクルを管理することで
it manages our both: passive behaviors such as sleep
それは睡眠などの受動的な行動ですが
but also the active side,
メラトニンのレベルが非常に低い日中に
which happens during the daytime, when melatonin levels are very low.
能動的な側面が活性化します
So it is this magnificently managed control,
このように見事に管理された制御は
extremely finely done by regulation of the nervous system
2つまたは3つの器官が作用し
to these two or three organs that relate
神経系の調節によって
to the sixth energy center.
6番目のエネルギーセンターの統治が 非常に極め細かく行われるのです
As laymen we seldom get a chance to understand
私たち素人にはこのように複雑な コミュニケーションに感心したり
or admire these complex communications,
私たちの中にデザインされている リズムとパターンを理解する機会は
rhythms and patterns that have been designed into us.
ほとんどは無いと思います
This is really very, very wonderful information, Dr. Ashish.
これは本当に素晴らしい情報ですね アシシュ博士
We would like to know the evolutionary significance
次に知りたいのは 進化的意義についてです
and where the center is most likely located?
そのセンターはどこに位置する可能性が 高いでしょうか?
So this center - hypothalamus - as you can imagine,
このセンターである視床下部は ご想像のとおり
the regulation of the body of an organism was a requirement
進化論の観点から見ると
from an evolutionary point of view,
生物の体の調節は必須でした
it's putting maybe the cart before the horse
それは本末転倒かもしれない
or effect before the cause.
または原因より先に結果が来るものです
But even as we start looking at again, the aquatic life forms,
水生生物から両生類や
and then amphibians and early terrestrial, so on and so forth,
初期の陸生生物の観察に戻ると
as the bodies became more complex, multicellular with more
体がより複雑になります
and more defined organ systems, cardiovascular system,
より明確な臓器系、心血管系
respiratory system, digestive system,
呼吸器系、消化器系など 多細胞化して
they needed a master control over that organism so as to survive.
生き残るためにその生物を支配する 主観的な制御を必要としていました
If any of these systems are not well controlled, it can go out of whack,
これらが適切に制御されていない場合 機能不全に陥る可能性があります
and then that starts creating its own issues.
そして、それが独自の問題を生み出し始めます
So which is why the hypothalamus is believed
だから視床下部は
that hypothalamic nuclei, like any organ in the brain,
視床下部「核」は 脳の他の器官と同様に
is like anything else, it's just a group of cells.
他のものと同様 単なる細胞の集まりです
So anything in the brain is composed of cells that are called neurons.
脳内のあらゆるものはニューロン と呼ばれる細胞で構成されています
The hypothalamic neurons, maybe not the organ,
視床下部のニューロンは 器官ではないかもしれないが
but the neurons have been found in very primitive life forms as well.
ニューロンは非常に原始的な生命体にも 発見されているのです
So that is the evolutionary relevance of this particular energy center, if you will,
これが、この特定のエネルギーセンターの 進化的関連性と言えるでしょう
as manifest through the existence of the anatomical organ,
解剖学的器官の存在を通して 明らかであるように
which is manifest in vertebrates,
これは脊椎動物に現れており
and particularly, of course, in the Homo sapiens as hypothalamus.
そして特にホモサピエンスにおいては 視床下部として機能します
So its evolutionary significance is profound,
その進化的意義は深い
without the hypothalamus or a hypothalamic like body,
視床下部または 視床下部に似た器官がなければ
controlling the entirety of our vegetative functions,
私たちの栄養機能の全体を 意識的に制御しなければなりません
which is why we don't have to think about how many times our heart has to beat,
私たちは心臓が何回鼓動しなければならないかを 考える必要がないのです
we don't have to think
考える必要はないのです
what should be the force of the digestive propulsive forces?
消化推進力の強さは どの程度であるべきでしょうか?
How many times should we breathe?
何回呼吸すればいいのでしょうか？
What is the extent of breathing?
呼吸の範囲はどのくらいですか？
All of these functions, that is circulatory system,
これらすべての機能 循環器系は
respiratory system or digestive system,
呼吸器系または消化器系
and the thousands and thousands of processes in the body that are controlled,
そして体内で制御されている何千ものプロセスでは
that needed that sort of system - you can think of it as,
そういうものが必要だったのです
as almost like a fly-by-wire technology that exists now in modern aircraft,
現代の航空機に搭載されている フライバイワイヤ技術に似たもので
but the pilot doesn't really have to think,
パイロットは実際には考える必要はなく
just switches on as a master computer that takes over
マスターコンピュータとして起動し 制御を引き継ぎます
and on a second to second, not even a minute to minute,
そして１秒１秒、１分１分どころか
just as the aircraft maintains its altitude, its speed, its direction,
飛行機が高度、速度、方向を 維持するのと同じように制御します
that's exactly how the hypothalamus functions.
まさにそれが視床下部の機能なのです
And that is its evolutionary significance.
そしてそれが進化上の重要性なのです
It has evolved to allow us to survive
私たちが生き残るために進化した
without having to put in a lot of cognitive effort,
認知的な努力をほとんどすることなく
conscious effort into our survival.
意識的な努力が私たちの生存に関わってきます
So that's basically its evolutionary importance.
つまり、それが基本的に 進化上の重要性なのです
It is located
それはちょうど先ほどお話しした
just maybe below the optic chiasma that we spoke about.
視交叉の下あたりでしょう
And it is again, very difficult to maybe just pinpoint
正確な場所を特定するのは 非常に難しいかもしれません
because it exists in the form of energy.
それはエネルギーの形で存在するからです
We discussed that in one of the first episodes.
私たちは最初のエピソードの１つで そのことについて議論しました
So these don't exist in the state of matter,
これらは物質の状態では存在しないので おそらくですが
but it's most likely situated, as we said,
先ほど言ったように
you draw a straight line from the middle of her forehead,
真ん中から後頭部に直線を引き
right at the back, and then from across from the top of her ears.
左右の耳の上を結ぶようにもう一本線を引くと
And where these two lines will intersect somewhere in the middle,
2本の線が交差します
just below the optic chiasma in that area
視交叉の領域のすぐ下に該当する場所
is where near the hypothalamus is probably where this energy center is located.
視床下部の近くに 位置していると考えられます
I really like the analogies that you use to explain complex concepts,
複雑な概念を説明するときに使う 比喩表現が本当に気に入っています
because if we do not have a lot of science background,
科学的な背景があまりなければ
it just gets so much easier for us to just understand that whole concept.
その概念全体を理解することが 私たちにとって非常に簡単になるからです
That's very, very beautifully explained, doctor.
それはとてもとても美しく 説明されています、博士
When we come to the functioning of the center,
センターの機能についてですが
how does it relate to the maintenance of balance
それは人類のバランスの維持と
within a human being?
どのように関係するのでしょうか？
And is there, is this related to a direct control of actions, emotions,
行動や感情、行動の能動的・受動的な側面
the active passive aspects of human behavior?
直接的な制御と関係しているのでしょうか？
Absolutely.
確実に関係しています
So as we said, the neuroendocrine system is closely linked to —
神経内分泌系がストレスとストレス管理に
there's so much literature on stress and stress management
寄与するという文献はたくさんあります
and what causes stress and whether stress is even
ストレスの原因は何なのか？
a physiologically good thing to have because it is something called eustress,
ストレスはユーストレスと呼ばれるもので 生理的に良いことなのです
distress, so on and so forth.
苦痛もありますが
But when we look at the normal physiologic functioning of a human being,
しかし、人間の通常の生理機能を見ると
it comprises a minute to minute or even a second to second awareness
それは1分ごと、あるいは1秒ごとの 意識から成り立っています
of our own selves as well as that of our surroundings.
私たち自身のことだけでなく 私たちの周囲のことも関係します
And it brings into focus our attention, our memories,
私たちの注意や私たちの記憶に 焦点を当てます
and we'll talk about this, of course, in the next episode as well.
もちろん、次のエピソードでも これについてお話します
Our memories, attention, our awareness,
私たちの記憶、注意、意識
our place within the universe around us,
私たちの周りの宇宙における私たちの位置
whether it is our societies, whether it is our families,
それが私たちの社会であろうと それが私たちの家族であろうと
whether it is our workplaces.
それが職場であろうと なかろうと
And in this minute to minute, literally, existential sort of environment,
そしてこの分刻みの 文字通り実存的な環境の中で
we react, we respond.
私たちは反応し、応答します
And we respond in a way that is a very complex integral,
私たちは非常に複雑な積分で 反応します
if you will, of who we are as individuals.
いわば、私たちが個人として どのような存在であるかということです
And who we are as individuals is again a function of our collective past,
そして、私たちが個人として何者であるかは 私たちの集合的な過去の機能です
our individual past, our cultures, our ethnic identities,
私たちの個人的な過去 文化、民族的アイデンティティ
our languages, our geographies, where we come from,
言語、地理、出身地
the way we were raised, not everybody's raised the same.
私たちが育てられた方法は 皆が同じように育てられたわけではありません
So whoever we are, this huge amalgam of our memories,
だから、私たちが誰であろうと この巨大な記憶の集合体は
of our conditionings, all are governed by what constitutes the brain.
私たちの条件付けはすべて 脳を構成するものによって支配されています
And within the brain, it is this energy center that plays a particular role,
脳内では、このエネルギーセンターが 特別な役割を果たしています
because it is also related to the notion of ego and superego.
それは自我と超自我の概念にも 関連しているからです
And we have these two institutions, there are other videos
これら2つの機関があり 他にもビデオがあります
that Sahaja Yoga gives us, that speak to it,
サハジャヨガが私たちに与えてくれるもの サハジャヨガについて語ってくれるもの
but it gives you that sense of I-ness versus the others.
しかし、それはあなたに 他者に対する「自分」という感覚を与えてくれます
And that is where this energy center comes into play.
ここで、このエネルギー センターが役に立ちます
So in individuals who are well balanced,
バランスの取れた人は
'balanced' is more of a metaphorical term
「バランスの取れた」というのは 比喩的な言葉で
or of a spiritual term, but individuals who do not react
精神的な言葉で不必要に
unnecessarily or excessively,
または過度に反応しない人を指します
if you see a cat and you start running in the opposite direction, that's a problem.
猫を見たら反対方向に走り出すならば それは問題です
If you see a tiger and you start running in the opposite direction, not a problem.
トラを見たら反対方向に走り始めても 問題ありません
Why?
なぜ？
Because although they both belong to the cat family,
どちらもネコ科に属していますが
those are two very different situations.
これらはまったく異なる2つの状況です
So that is where this center comes into play.
そこでこのセンターが役に立ちます
And if there are individuals who react in a very different way,
全く異なる反応をする人がいたとしても
in these kinds of situations, those are very generic situations,
こういった状況は非常に一般的です
very obvious ones.
非常に明白なものです
But that is what defines a healthy state of this energy center versus not.
しかし、それがこのエネルギー センターの 健全な状態とそうでない状態を定義します
And therefore, it is very important to keep this energy center
ですから、ここを維持することは 非常に重要です
in a very healthy state or might say in a balanced state
非常に健康な状態、あるいは バランスの取れた状態と言えるでしょう
by developing through the Sahaj meditation process,
サハジャ瞑想のプロセスを通して発展することで
what we call a balanced, forgiving and a charitably disposed personality.
いわゆるバランスのとれた 寛容で慈悲深い性格です
Because that way, as you can now see the function of the hypothalamus,
なぜなら、視床下部の働きがわかるように
it does not have to secrete these hormones that will raise your blood pressure,
血圧を上げるホルモンを分泌する必要はないので
that will raise your heart rate, that will allow you to react more aggressively
心拍数が上がり攻撃的だと感じる環境に
to an environment which you perceive to be aggressive,
より前向きに反応できるようになります
which may not be aggressive, which may not be threatening to you.
それは攻撃的ではないかもしれませんし あなたにとって脅威ではないかもしれません
So life then becomes more a matter of perception rather than reality.
そうすると、人生は現実の問題ではなく むしろ認識の問題になります
And the calibration of one's response to that environment
そしてその環境に対する 反応の調整の問題です
is what defines an individual from being relatively
個人を相対的に定義するもの
what we call in conventional terms as reactive, immature,
従来の言葉で言うと 瞬発的反応や未熟さから
to somebody who is, we say, more mature, sagacious.
より成熟した、より賢明な人へと
So think of a Lincoln or a Gandhi like personality
リンカーンやガンジーのような性格を考えてみましょう
relative to somebody who is much more reactive or gets easily ruffled,
反応が激しく、すぐに動揺してしまう人に比べて
we say, we just know some people who are just calm, more composed,
私たちは、ただ落ち着いていますし 落ち着いている人を知っているだけだと言います
they don't react that negatively or excessively.
彼らはそれほど否定的または過剰に反応しません
And that is where it kind of comes in, the importance of this center
そして、このセンターの重要性がここに現れます
to maintain that balance within us, right action and right behavior.
私たちの内部でバランスを維持し 正しい行動と正しい振る舞いを保つことです
It does not mean we remain constantly passive.
それは私たちが常に受動的であり続けることを 意味するものではありません
we remain constantly active.
それは私たちが常に活動し続けることを
Where is that fine balance?
その微妙なバランスはどこにあるのでしょうか?
How do you calibrate back to that aircraft?
その航空機に合わせてどうやって調整するのですか?
How do you maintain your speed, your altitude and your course
速度、高度、進路をどうやって維持するか
from a, shall we say, an emotional perspective
感情的な観点から言えば
or from a spiritual perspective is what this center is really about.
あるいは精神的な観点から見ることが このセンターの真の目的です
And that's why it plays such a vital role in human spirituality.
だからこそ、それは人間の精神性において 非常に重要な役割を果たしているのです
Thank you, Dr. Ashish, for bringing up that very wonderful point,
アシシュ博士、素晴らしい点を指摘して頂き ありがとうございます
a very relevant point about the level of reactions that we all may have.
私たち全員が示すかもしれない 反応のレベルに非常に関連のある点です
And it is for each of us to, just look inside us, look around us
そして私たち一人一人が自分の内面を見つめ 周りを見渡すことが大切です
to see where we find just giving reactions more than needed.
必要以上に反応している箇所を確認します
Like you explained with the example of the cat and the tiger responses
猫とトラの反応の例で説明したように
to a similar situation or a different situation,
同様の状況や異なる状況に
how they need to be.
彼らがどうあるべきか
But this is something that we are seeing a lot around us on social media
しかし、これはソーシャルメディアの 様々なプラットフォームで
and different platforms.
よく見られる現象です
So, anything that you want to add to that
私たちがいる環境に対して
just so that we can be more aware of our surroundings,
周囲の状況をより意識できるように
our environments where we are?
何かご意見はありますか？
Fabulous. That's such a great point, Monika,
素晴らしい。それは本当に素晴らしい指摘です
if we think of our evolution,
私たちの進化を考えてみると
but we don't have to go back to the aquatic stage.
しかし、水中段階に戻る必要はありません
Just about 100 years ago, just about 50 years ago,
100年前や50年前には
there was no social media,
ソーシャルメディアはありませんでしたし
television and media did not play such a big role in our lives.
テレビやメディアは私たちの生活の中で それほど大きな役割を果たしていませんでした
People had a much more quote-unquote pastoral lifestyle,
人々はいわゆる田園的な生活を送っていました
certainly pre-industrial societies.
産業革命以前の社会です
But even in post-industrial societies, it was not that much of a deal.
しかし、脱工業化社会においても それはそれほど大きな問題ではありませんでした
This influence of media and the environment around us,
メディアや私たちを取り巻く環境の影響は
there were communities, there were neighbors,
コミュニティがあり、隣人がいましたが
but with the advent of social media, particularly, life has become very reactive.
特にソーシャルメディアの出現により 生活は非常に反応的なものになりました
You are part of some kind of a social media platform,
あなたは何らかのソーシャルメディア プラットフォームに参加しています
whichever it is, with your friends, with your office colleagues or neighbours,
友達や職場の同僚、近所の人など、どんな人でも
as the case may be, you read a post about a topic,
場合によっては、あるトピックに関する 投稿を読みます
whether it is political, whether it is social, whether it is cultural,
それが政治的であろうと 社会的・文化的なものであろうと
and the brain processes it.
脳がそれを処理します
Within our brain is a very important group
私たちの脳の中には 非常に重要なグループがあります
of neurotransmitters - one of them is dopamine.
神経伝達物質の１つがドーパミンです
Dopamine is a pleasure giving molecule.
ドーパミンは快楽を与える分子です
Whenever we do or feel something pleasurable,
何か楽しいことを行い感じるたびに
there is a part of the brain called a substantia nigra that secretes dopamine.
脳には黒質と呼ばれるドーパミンを 分泌する部分があります
Dopamine gives us that high, that rush.
ドーパミンは私たちに 高揚感と興奮感を与えます
And where social media comes in, social media algorithms.
そして、ソーシャル メディアが登場するところでは ソーシャル メディア アルゴリズムが登場します
I'm not a tech expert, but I saw a couple of documentaries,
私は技術の専門家ではありませんが いくつかのドキュメンタリーを見ました
and they explained beautifully that there is a full blown understanding
そして彼らは、完全な理解があることを
of the human nervous system, and particularly of how the dopamine
人間の神経系で特にドーパミンがどのように
system works to produce that rush.
そのラッシュを生み出すように機能するのかを 美しく説明しました
So we are constantly through algorithms that are designed to generate that rush within us.
私たちは常に高揚感を生み出すように 設計された手順を実行しているのです
So we are constantly hooked onto it.
だから私たちは常に夢中です
We are given content or fed content that is based on these algorithms
これらのアルゴリズムに基づいた コンテンツを提供され
that grab our attention and hold it.
私たちの注意を引いて、それを維持するものに 夢中になっています
And that is where this center is also where it's damaged the most,
そしてこのセンターは最も被害を 受けた場所でもあります
because it keeps us on this endless loop.
なぜなら、それは私たちをこの無限ループに 陥らせ続けるからです
We are essentially like animals that are on treadmills,
私たちは本質的にルームランナーの上で 走る動物のようなものです
that you're constantly fed that morphine of information, if you will,
いわば、情報のモルヒネを常に与えられているのです
and that triggers dopamine within us.
そしてそれは私たちの体内でドーパミンを刺激します
And that gives us that sense of high and that high keeps us hooked onto social media.
それが私たちに高揚感を与え その高揚感が私たちを ソーシャルメディアに夢中にさせるのです
So the Agnya Chakra or the sixth energy center probably in the entirety of human civilization,
記録された歴史と記録されていない歴史において これは断じて誇張ではなく、人類史上
recorded and unrecorded history, and this is not a hyperbole,
アグニャチャクラ 6番目のエネルギーセンターは
I genuinely feel it has never probably been more stressed due to social media.
ソーシャルメディアのせいで これほどストレスがかかったことは かつてなかったでしょう
But what is the solution?
しかし解決策は何でしょうか?
It's easy to identify a problem, but then what is the solution?
問題を特定するのは簡単ですが 解決策は何でしょうか?
The solution is that through meditation,
解決策は瞑想を通して
we can begin to stay away from that rush.
私たちはその慌ただしさから 遠ざかり始めることができます
We don't need that rush.
そんなに急ぐ必要はないのです
You don't need to constantly feel your presence on social media
ソーシャルメディアで常に自分の存在を 感じる必要はありません
or see what is the latest post out there?
最新の投稿が何かを確認しますか?
Or if you posted something, has somebody read it or not?
あるいは、何かを投稿した場合 誰かがそれを読んだかどうか?
How many likes have you received?
いくつ「いいね！」をもらいましたか？
Or have you not received it?
それとも受け取っていませんか？
So if you have not received anything, no responses,
もし何も受け取っていなければ 返信もなければ
you kind of go down and then that dopamine rush goes down,
気分が落ち込み ドーパミンの放出も止まります
you'll start feeling depressed.
気分が落ち込み始めるでしょう
And we see this particularly in teenagers,
これは特に10代の若者に多く見られます
which is why the US Congress is acting very wisely.
だからこそ、米国議会は非常に 賢明な行動をとっているのです
So to try to see if these social media platforms
これらのソーシャルメディア媒体が作り出す
can actually be modulated
精神衛生上の問題を避けるために
to avoid creating mental health issues
実際に調整できます
for susceptible age groups such as teenagers,
10代の若者などの影響を受けやすい年齢層では
whose use can lead to extreme outcomes.
使用すると極端な結果を招く可能性があります
So yes, that's a phenomenal point that you raised.
それはあなたの指摘した驚くべき問題点です
And this energy center in particular plays a very critical role
このエネルギーセンターは ソーシャル メディアの影響を受けるので
in either being susceptible and being influenced by social media.
非常に重要な役割を果たします
But then through meditative practice, such as the Sahaj meditation,
サハジャ瞑想のような瞑想の実践を通して
you can actually maintain a healthy boundary.
実際に健全な境界を維持することができます
So nobody's saying here, you should not interact with social media,
だから誰もソーシャルメディアに関わってはいけない とは言っていません
not use social media, social media is a way of life now.
現代ではソーシャルメディアを使わないのではなく ソーシャルメディアは生活の一部となっているのです
We all have to live with it.
私たちは皆、それとともに 生きていかなければなりません
The question is how and to what extent?
問題は、どのように そしてどの程度までかということです
And I think with what you have shared, it seems like,
そしてあなたがシェアしてくれた内容から
with this meditation, not only an individual is going to benefit,
この瞑想によって個人が恩恵を受けるだけでなく
in the ability to self-regulate themselves,
自己制御能力において
it'll also impact the society at large.
社会全体にも影響を及ぼすでしょう
Think about it like, if each of us just gets a little bit better
考えてみてください 私たち一人一人が少しでも良くなれば
in terms of how we react,
私たちがどう反応するかという点では
it's really going to impact the health of the society as well.
それは社会の健全性にも 本当に影響を与えるでしょう
Thank you, Dr. Ashish.
アシシュ博士、ありがとうございます
Thank you so much for this very wonderful information.
とても素晴らしい情報をありがとうございました
And we look forward to speaking to you again soon next time.
次回またお話できることを楽しみにしております
Thank you Monika, thanks for having me.
モニカさん、ありがとう 招待してくれてありがとう
Thank you.
ありがとうございます
We would encourage our audiences to follow
視聴者の皆様には是非この後も 体験していただきたいと思います
the guided meditation video by the founder of this meditation,
この瞑想の創始者 シュリ・マタジ・ニルマラ・デヴィによる
Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi.
ガイド付き誘導瞑想です
And do join us next time for yet another exciting conversation
次回もまたアシシュ・プラダン博士との
with Dr. Ashish Pradhan.
刺激的な会話を楽しみましょう
Thank you.
ありがとうございます
Shri Mataji: Today we are going to understand the center of Agnya,
シュリ・マタジ： 今日はアグニャのセンターを理解します
Agnya chakra which is placed on the crossing of the optic chiasma.
視交叉の交差点に位置するアグニャ チャクラ
The nerves that supply the eyes go backwards in the opposite direction,
目に栄養を送る神経は逆方向に逆行し
and wherever they cross, this subtle center is situated.
そしてそれらが交差するところには必ず
It has a continuous connection with the other center
延髄を通って他のセンターと連続的に接続している
through the medulla oblongata.
この精妙なセンターが存在します
This center has got two petals and this subtle center on one side
この中心には2枚の花びらがあり 一方は目を通して作用します
acts through the eyes and at the back of the head where you have some protrusion.
他方では後頭部の突出している部分に作用します
This is the physical side of the center.
これはセンターの物理的な側面です
The people who talk of the third eye, this is the third eye.
第三の目について語る人々 これが第三の目です
Keep your eyes closed.
目を閉じてください
First of all, please put your right hand on your heart.
まずは右手を胸に当ててください
All the time the left hand is towards Me.
常に左手は私の方に向いています
Now, here you have to say in your heart, with all sincerity, Mother, am I the Spirit?
あなたは心の中で心からこう言います 「母よ、私は聖霊でしょうか？」
Ask the question three times in your heart.
心の中で3回質問してください
This is a very fundamental question.
これは非常に基本的な質問です
Now bring the right hand on to the left hand side of your stomach,
右手をお腹の左側に当てます
in the upper part.
上部にあります
Here press it.
ここを押してください
Now this is the center of your mastery, your guidance, your guru Tattva, as they say.
あなたの熟達、あなたの指導 あなたのグル・タットヴァのセンターです
So ask a question, Mother, am I my own master?
質問してください
This is the question to be asked three times.
3回です
Mother, am I my own master?
「母よ、私は自分自身の指導者ですか?」
Now bring your right hand down below in the lower part of the abdomen.
次に右手を下腹部まで下ろします
Now this is the center from which all the Divine work is done,
すべての神の仕事が行われる中心です
all the pure work is done.
純粋な作業はすべて完了しました
So to ask six times, because this center has got six petals,
この中心には6つの花びらがあるので 6回願います
Mother, please give me pure knowledge.
「母よ、私に純粋な知識を与えてください」
Six times you just ask.
6回はただ願うです
As a result of this asking the Kundalini starts getting awakened.
祈りの結果としてクンダリーニが目覚め始めます
Now to help the Kundalini to rise you have to cooperate with Her.
クンダリーニの上昇を助けるには クンダリーニと協力しなければなりません
So please put your right hand on the left hand side
右手を左側に置いてください
in the upper part of your abdomen and press it on the stomach.
腹部の上部にあるので 手を押し付けます
Now here you have to say with full confidence,
あなたは自信を持って こう言わなければなりません
to help the Kundalini to rise, Mother, I am my own master.
クンダリーニの上昇を助けるために 「母よ、私は自分自身の指導者です」
This you have to say ten times.
10回言わなければなりません
These are the ten commandments which you have to say,
あなたが言わなければならない十戒です
that Mother, I am my own master.
「母よ、私は自分自身の指導者です」
Now, ten times with full confidence.
自信を持って10回言いましょう
Now please raise your right hand to your heart.
右手を胸に当ててください
Now here you have to say, again with full confidence,
ここでもう一度、自信を持ってこう言います
Mother, I am the Spirit.
「母よ、私は聖霊です」
This is the truth, you are the Spirit.
これは真実です あなたは聖霊なのです
But you have to say with full confidence, Mother, I am the Spirit.
あなたは完全な自信を持ってこう言わなければなりません 「母よ、私は聖霊です」
This you have to say twelve times.
12回です
Now one has to know that God Almighty is the ocean of love.
全能の神は愛の海である ということを知らなければなりません
But above all He is the ocean of forgiveness.
しかし、何よりも 神は赦しの海なのです
So He forgives.
だから神は許すのです
Whatever wrong you do He forgives.
あなたがどんな悪いことをしても 神は許してくれます
So don't feel guilty and put your right hand across
だから罪悪感を感じずに 右手を差し伸べてください
on the left hand side in the corner which is made by your neck and your shoulder.
首と肩が作る角の左側にあります
Now here you have to say again with full confidence,
ここでもう一度自信を持って 言わなければなりません
sixteen times, Mother, I am not guilty.
16回です「母よ、私は無実です」
Please say it, Mother, I am not guilty.
「母よ、私は無罪です」
Sixteen times.
16回です
I am not guilty at all.
私には全く罪がありません
Please say it.
言ってください
Now raise your hand across on your forehead and it's a very important center.
額の上で手を上げてください そこは非常に重要なセンターです
Here you have to say from your heart, Mother, I forgive everyone.
ここで、あなたは心からこう言います 「母よ、私は全ての人を許します」
Please say it from your heart.
心から言ってください
How many times is not the point.
何回かということは重要ではありません
Mother, I forgive everyone.
「母よ、私は全ての人を許します」
Now some would say that it's very difficult to forgive.
許すのは非常に難しいと言う人も いると思います
But it's a myth that we do not forgive or we forgive.
しかし、私たちが許さない あるいは許すというのは神話です
We do not do anything in both the cases.
どちらの場合も、実際は何も行いません
But if we don't forgive then we play into wrong hands.
しかし、許さなければ 私たちは悪者の手に渡ってしまうのです
So please say from your heart, Mother, I forgive everyone.
ですから、心から言ってください 「母よ、私はみんなを許します」
Now please take your hand on the back agnya, the same center, on the back side of your head
次に、アグニャチャクラの後ろ側 後頭部に手を当ててください
and allow your head to rest on it and push it back a little bit.
手に頭を乗せて、少し後ろに押します
Now here you have to say for your satisfaction,
満足のために言いましょう
because you always feel guilty, that, O Divine, if I have done anything wrong,
なぜなら、あなたはいつも罪悪感を感じているからです
please forgive me.
「神よ、私が何か悪いことをしたら 私を許してください
Please forgive me, from your heart.
どうかお許し下さい」 誠実に言いましょう
Stretch your hand fully and put your center of your palm
次に手を完全に伸ばし 手のひらの中央を頭頂部に置きます
on top of the fontanel bone area, which was a very soft bone in your childhood.
泉門骨の上の部分です 子供の頃は非常に柔らかい骨でした
Press it hard.
強く押してください
Press hard your scalp.
頭皮を強く押します
Now you have to move it seven times saying one thing, which you have to ask for,
今度はそれを7回動かして 1つのことを言わなければなりません
Mother, please give us My Self-realization, because I cannot force on you.
「母よ、どうか私たちに私の自己実現を与えてください」 私はあなたに強制することはできません
So you have to ask for it.
あなたがお願いしなければなりません
Seven times press it hard and move it seven times very hard.
7 回強く押し、動かします
Slowly saying that.
ゆっくりと行いましょう